<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
 *
 * Overview SampleSTAT
 * Copyright (c) 2019 - Hani A. Ibrahim
 *
-->
<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:scilab="http://www.scilab.org" xml:lang="en_US" xml:id="samplestat_overview">
	<refnamediv>
		<refname>Overview</refname>
		<refpurpose>An overview of the SampleSTAT toolbox for univariate data.</refpurpose>
	</refnamediv>
	<refsection>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
        This toolbox provides elementary tests for the evaluation of univariate measuring data which were generated by natural scientists and engineers in the first place. These data have to be normal distributed. SampleSTAT is focused on small sample sizes but offers routines for bigger distributions (&gt;30 values), too. It offers functions for calculates the range of dispersion of the values and the mean regarding a given statistical confidence level. Furthermore it provides tests on outliers and a method to test the data for normal distribution. 
    </para>
		<important>
			<para>
		These routines are applicable for normal distributed data ONLY.
	</para>
		</important>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Measures of Variation:</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
		   Calculates the stray areas of values and mean of normal distributed data. That gives you more information of the quality of your data as the standard deviation (S.D.) of samples can do. S.D. has an statistical confidence of 68%. Stray area (of values) can provide a confidence level of 95%, 99% and 99.9%. The trust area (stray area of the mean) gives you information of the confidence of your mean with a probability of 95%, 99% and 99.9%.
	   </para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Outlier Tests:</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
		   Provides test to determine whether an extreme value is an outlier or not. Test are available for small and bigger distributions.
       </para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Tests for Normal Distribution:</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
		   All routines are applicable for normal distributed data only. To test for normal distribution, tests are provided.
       </para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<para>
        These functions are good to extend the built-in functions mean(), stdev(), max(), min(), median() and can be extended by routines of the toolboxes "Stixbox" and "Distfun".
    </para>
	</refsection>
	<refsection>
		<title>Functions - Measures of Variation</title>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>ST_strayarea:</term>
				<listitem>
					<para> Calculates the stray area (range of dispersion of the values) of univariate data for a statistical confidence level (95%, 99%, 99.9%) and level of significance (0.5, 0.01, 0.001), resp. </para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>ST_trustarea:</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Calculates the trust area (range of dispersion of the mean) of univariate data and for a statistical confidence level (95%, 99%, 99.9%) and level of significance (0.5, 0.01, 0.001), resp. and is the standard deviation of the mean. </para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>ST_studentfactor:</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Determines the student factor for an amount of numbers and for a statistical confidence level (95%, 99%, 99.9%) and level of significance (0.5, 0.01, 0.001), resp.- service function for ST_strayarea and ST_trustarea</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</refsection>
	<refsection>
		<title>Functions - Tests on Outliers</title>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>ST_deandixon:</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
		   This test for outliers is eminently suitable for small sample sizes; for samples having more than 30 observations the test for significance of Pearson and Hartley can be used as well.
	   </para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>ST_pearsonhartley:</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>For random samples larger than 30 objects possible outliers may be identified by using the significance thresholds of Pearson and Hartley. 
	   </para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>ST_nalimov:</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
		   This test on outliers provides a quick hint for all sample sizes and is often used in German publications.
	   </para>
					<important>
						<para>
	   	   There is some scientific discussion about this test. It is thus recommended to use other tests instead of the Nalimov test (Dean-Dixon test for small samples, the test of Pearson and Hartley for larger ones).
       </para>
					</important>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>ST_outlier:</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
			  Provide two basic tests on outliers based on standard deviation (S.D.) or inter-quartile range (IQR). It should be applied to sample sizes larger than 10 better more than 25. For small sample sizes the Dean-Dixon test is recommended.
         </para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</refsection>
	<refsection>
		<title>Functions - Distribution tests</title>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>ST_shapirowilk:</term>
				<listitem>
					<para> 
		   This test for normality exhibiting high power, leading to good results even with a small number of observations, especially in comparison to Chi-Square or Kolmogorov-Smirnov tests. 
	   </para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>ST_skewness:</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
 			Calculates the skew value helping to determine if a sample distribution is skewed (right or left) or not.  This is important to chose the correct method on ST_outlier.
        </para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</refsection>
	<refsection>
		<title>Authors</title>
		<para>
		Hani A. Ibrahim - hani.ibrahim@gmx.de
	</para>
	</refsection>
	<refsection>
		<title>Bibliography</title>
		<para>R. Kaiser, G. Gottschalk; "Elementare Tests zur Beurteilung von Meßdaten", BI Hochschultaschenbücher, Bd. 774, Mannheim 1972.</para>
		<para>Lohringer, H., "Grundlagen der Statistik", Oct, 10th, 2012, http://www.statistics4u.info/</para>
		<para>Shapiro, Wilk: "An Analysis of Variance Test for Normality", Biometrika, Vol. 52, No. 3/4. (Dec., 1965), pp. 591-611.</para>
	</refsection>
</refentry>
